Mama!
-What is it?
-Let me see.
Mama, am I dying?
Quite the contrary, Remedios.
ONE HUNDRED YEARS OF SOLITUDE
It was a fatiguing effort,
but by the date of the ceremony,
Remedios had become
as adept in the ways of the world
as the rest of her sisters.
Aureliano, on the other hand,
who wore the same boots
he would wear a few years later
as he stood in front of the firing squad,
had a lump in his throat.
You're more handsome than ever.
Where's Rebeca?
Hmm?
Thank you.
Per Úrsula's instructions,
Rebeca was to get married on the same day.
Miss Rebeca,
someone's here to see you.
But the night before,
Pietro Crespi had received a letter with
the news of the imminent death of Giulia,
his mother.
And he immediately left for the capital.
Rebeca.
Not a single of Pietro's letters
could do justice to your beauty.
Giulia?
Mm.
Where's Pietro?
I'd like to see him before the ceremony.
That's not
your actual wedding gown, is it?
Hmm.
Are you here?
One should not
subjugate life everywhere.
-Life…
-Hmm.
Not today, José Arcadio.
Not today. Hmm?
The wedding is the easy part.
Relax.
So that their union will be blessed
from this day forward.
Amen.
The love of God
shines upon the two of you today,
unwavering, just as love should be.
Aureliano, take the ring
and repeat after me.
I, Aure--
-Oh my goodness.
-Wow. Did he drop it?
It'll hit one. It's rolling.
That day… would reveal
the natural grace and composure
that Remedios would forever show
in the face of adversity.
I, Aureliano Buendía, take thee…
…Remedios Moscote, to be my wife.
…Remedios Moscote, to be my wife…
…to have and to hold…
…until death do us part.
I, Remedios Moscote, take thee,
Aureliano Buendía, to be my husband,
to have and to hold, for better or worse,
in sickness and in health,
until death do us part.
What have you done?
-Let this union be an example.
-Sh.
A reminder to always adhere to
the right way of doing things,
just like what Mr. Apolinar Moscote
has brought to Macondo.
Hmm.
I now pronounce you husband and wife.
-They've outdone themselves.
-Yes. Yes.
And over here are
the Márquezes and the Visbals.
Ah.
Good evening.
I understand you are some of the founders?
-Mm-hmm.
-Indeed. Gerineldo Márquez.
Delighted.
Well, Father Nicanor Reyna
has done us the honor
of rescheduling his spiritual activities
in Santa Marta to be able to come join us.
No, Mrs. Leonor, you're too kind.
The honor is entirely mine. Believe me.
-How are you?
-Pleasure, Father. Isabel.
-Ah!
-I hope Macondo has been to your liking.
Well, you bet it has.
And now with God's presence,
it's been even better.
-Walk with me.
-Let's go.
-Thank you.
-What?
Calm down. Relax.
I understand, but we're at a wedding,
my dear. Just be polite.
I can't even imagine
everything that you've had to do
to support your family
on your own, Mrs. Buendía.
Thankfully,
I'm no stranger to work, Father Nicanor.
Right.
Well, I'll pray
for the both of you anyway.
Oh, my dear, don't worry.
I know my Pietro.
He'll marry you as soon as he returns.
Your marriage will be a wonderful one.
You'll make a beautiful bride.
You are going to make a beautiful couple.
Rebeca, where are you going?
It was you
who sent that letter, wasn't it?
Rebeca… enough.
I could've done
much worse than that to you.
I could have simply killed you.
-Would you like to dance, Amaranta?
-Sure.
-I'd love to.
-All right.
Where's my mother?
We can get married today.
Father Nicanor is still here.
I have the dress.
Everything's set up already.
I can't do it without her.
I'd never forgive myself.
Rebeca.
We will be together
for the rest of our lives.
All we need is time.
We do not die when we must,
but when we can.
We do not die when we must…
…but when we can.
Remedios took upon herself
the costly chore
of tending to José Arcadio Buendía.
She would keep his hair and beard free
of lice and nits. And most remarkably…
How did you…
…over the course of a few months…
What'd you say?
…she succeeded in communicating with him.
Metus? Miedo?
Yes, I'm afraid of care.
All right, ants,
no one will see you if you come this way.
No, no. If you take that path…
Watch out!
Do you see now?
Her arrival brought
a breath of joy to the Buendías.
Remedios, come here.
I'll teach you how to make our candy.
♪ De amor, eres mi bien ♪
♪ Tienes la gracia, canta, pajarito… ♪
Oh, my dear,
what a lovely voice you have.
Her vitality overflowed
the walls of the house.
Senorita Rebeca Buendía,
may I have this dance?
Hmm.
One, two, three.
One, two, three. One, two, three.
Very good!
And spin!
Perfect!
Good morning, world.
And she spun like a whirlwind
of good health through the corridors.
Good morning, José Arcadio.
Good morning, Remedios.
Good morning, Visitación.
Good morning.
Hmm.
Good morning, Mrs. Buendía.
Good morning, my dear.
As for Aureliano,
he had found in her presence
the motivation he needed
to keep on living.
Did you do that?
You can't be in here.
I'm sorry, Arcadio.
I thought you'd like a little coffee.
And she was…
Thanks.
…the last person Arcadio thought
about before he died.
Remedios, stay still.
I didn't say anything sooner,
because I didn't want
to ruin your wedding.
I know this is a problem, Aureliano…
but I already have two sons,
and he deserves a family.
All right, then.
I'll do it.
But you shouldn't have come here
unannounced like this.
It's all right.
My love.
-I'm sorry, and I promise to explain--
-Aureliano!
How could you, Aureliano?
Hmm.
It was before… I asked for
Remedios's hand in marriage--
It doesn't matter!
You'll make her raise a bastard?
What did you just say?
This child will always be a Buendía.
You better listen to me closely,
Úrsula Iguarán.
I will never permit you to treat my son
the same way that you treated Arcadio!
Fine then.
We'll see what your in-laws have to say
when they find out that you have a son.
We'll wait and see.
We will.
Does he have a name already?
He'll have mine and my brother's names.
Aureliano José.
I'll convince Nicanor
to baptize the boy tomorrow.
As long as he has God's blessing
and we keep it secret,
I don't think we have a problem.
Do you agree?
I agree.
Welcome to
the Kingdom of the Lord.
It's okay. There you go.
Sh.
Hold him tight.
And how long will you be staying, Father?
Pietro and I would love to organize
our wedding while you are still here.
Well, no need to rush things, darling,
because Father Nicanor
has decided to stay here.
Mm-hmm.
It's incredible what you have achieved
in the middle of nowhere, Mrs. Buendía.
What surprises me the most, though,
is that in the 30 years
since you founded this town
no one has ever thought of
adding a church.
The truth is, we've never needed a church
to bargain with God, Father Nicanor.
Ah, but see, you cannot bargain
with God, ma'am.
The Scriptures make that very clear.
Mrs. Buendía, has it ever occurred to you
that perhaps that horrific plague
that struck years ago
was God's way
of punishing you for being sinful?
Well, does Úrsula have to answer
for the people of Macondo?
No, no, no. Of course not.
Of course she doesn't have to. No.
Just last night,
I was dreaming about the church.
-Mm!
-Mm-hmm.
It was the biggest one in Colombia,
with windows from floor to ceiling,
human-sized saints,
and an organ…
an organ just like Notre Dame has.
We've already made
a contribution, of course.
-Mm.
-We're hopeful that other people join in.
With the grace of God
and the help of our good town,
we could be opening
our church doors in three years.
Rebeca would be so fortunate.
You'll have the honor of inaugurating
the church with your wedding.
No!
Don't misunderstand me.
It would be an honor
to get married at your church,
but I don't believe
we must wait that long.
But you would have a union
that is blessed by God.
Yeah, don't you want that?
-Isn't Remedios's marriage blessed?
-Rebeca.
Why do we have to wait three years?
The two of them got married at home.
Because everybody in this family
turned conservative overnight.
What did you just say?
-That you all turned conservative over--
-Just shut your mouth!
This entire town has been built
collectively, Father Nicanor.
I am sure that the church
will be ready much sooner
than any of you can imagine.
As for your wedding,
there will be plenty of time
to plan the ceremony you deserve.
Remedios was right.
You're a cultured man.
Mm. No one ever taught you to knock, huh?
Just let yourself in?
We Moscotes are curious.
What do you want?
Arcadio,
I got the government
to give us the resources
to build a school in Macondo,
but I still haven't found
a teacher that wants to stay
and who'd be willing
to take care of the facilities full-time.
Well, I'm sorry but I'm not interested in
working under or answering to anyone.
I have too many things on my plate to be
sticking my nose in your business, son.
So, what do you say?
I'm still waiting for an apology.
Where are you going, Arcadio?
You have an extra room now.
You don't have to say anything.
I should've left a while ago.
-Excuse me.
-Don't make things difficult.
-I don't understand--
-Anybody can claim to be a doctor.
Show some respect.
I don't know what kind of papers you want.
-Papers that show--
-Not giving you anything!
In this entire region,
no one has ever demanded
I show a permit from the government
that allows me to practice.
Listen to me. Unless you can
come back with the civil code
and can point out an actual law
that proves to me I must show you
anything other than my medical diplomas,
I'm going to have to ask you to leave.
You're scaring away potential customers.
Please stay away.
Apologies, sir.
No one's stood up to those guys
in a long time, you know?
Maybe it's because you all need
someone to remind you of your rights.
Doctor Alirio Noguera. Homeopath.
-Pleasure.
-Arcadio.
And I run the school.
You don't say.
It's a big responsibility
to deal with those boys.
If you ever want to talk
or need some medicine,
you know where to find me.
PUBLIC SCHOOL
At least for some time,
the school freed Arcadio from the weight
of that old familiar bitterness.
Alchemy…
Alchemy has always obsessed
some of the biggest geniuses in history,
for all of these individuals set out
to find the famous philosopher's stone!
The… the philosopher's stone?
Judging by your faces,
you probably have no clue what that is.
The problem is,
Gónzalez doesn't know a thing.
He really doesn't.
Then come to the front
and teach the class yourself, Rojas.
All right. All right.
Staying on course is necessary.
-Hmm?
-Enough, José Arcadio.
If you're gonna talk,
at least say something useful.
Thank you, sweetheart.
Thank you both.
All right, come here.
What's the matter?
What's wrong?
Aureliano,
you've been married for months now.
What do you think's wrong with her?
Are we giving Aureliano José a sibling?
Could you two knit a white one?
Of course we don't know the sex yet,
but I would love for the baby's aunts
to make their first gift.
The love
that Aureliano and Remedios inspired
in both their families was so deep,
that the moment she announced
she was expecting a child,
even Rebeca and Amaranta declared a truce.
But you made a promise, sir!
We're talking about the house of the Lord.
Father, sir, maybe if the Lord
had paid us what he owes us,
we'd be finished by now.
How am I supposed to collect
the tithe if I can't open the church?
-The money will come from the tithe.
-From the what?
-You're gonna pay us with the tithe?
-With the tithe. Yes of course!
-Father, sir. Don't worry…
-How long have they been at it?
One month.
Seems like they ran out of money.
-God can punish without a rod or a whip.
-Let's fit the tiles.
Take your time.
I don't want
things falling on my head.
Father…
Run away with me.
And where would we go?
Everything I have is right here.
-What happened?
-Nothing.
It's all good, Mrs. Úrsula.
Hmm.
♪ Kyrie eleison… ♪
Not having collected enough
to even pay for the doors…
♪ Kyrie… ♪
…Nicanor went through the town
with a little bell,
summoning people to an open-air mass.
♪ Kyrie… ♪
Many went out of curiosity.
Some did so out of nostalgia.
♪ Kyrie… ♪
Others went because they did not want
God to take their disdain
for his intermediary as a personal insult.
Now you will all witness the Lord's
irrefutable and extraordinary
proof of power and strength.
The boy who had been
helping him handed him a cup.
It was full of thick chocolate,
which he drank without taking
a pause to breathe.
Is this happening?
-It's magic.
-I can't believe what I'm seeing.
No one doubted
the divine nature of the demonstration…
except for José Arcadio Buendía.
It's quite simple.
He discovered the fourth state of matter.
No.
-Hmm.
-This proves God's existence beyond doubt.
You cannot fool me
with your magic tricks.
Until I see God in a daguerreotype,
I won't believe in your artifices.
What did he say?
What is he saying?
He said he's always wanted
to see God in a daguerreotype.
And so, they discovered
that the devilish jargon
José Arcadio had been speaking was Latin.
Uh, Mrs. Buendía,
might I have a word with you?
Why don't you go lay down?
Your body needs rest.
I just wanted to share something with you.
As you may have noticed,
I've done everything in my power
to bring faith into the homes of Macondo.
Mm.
But at this pace,
with the donations we have,
I won't finish this church in three years.
At best, I'll finish it in ten.
So I wanted to ask you
if you could, perhaps, help me
by speaking to your fellow neighbors--
It's best if we don't burden Úrsula
with that responsibility, Father.
God knows things happen
when they need to happen.
-Ah, amen.
-Hmm.
-Amen.
-Either way, what's the rush? Huh?
-I'll see you later.
-See you later, ma'am.
You're driving my kids crazy.
Now they want me to
buy them some chemistry books.
That right?
Yes. Congratulations on your job.
-Thank you.
-Come on.
Without knowing
the secret of his parentage,
Pilar Ternera became just as irresistible
of an obsession for him
as she'd been for his father.
He would look for her,
and would find her by the trail
of her smell of smoke,
not knowing exactly how to approach her.
Another one?
Thank you.
Here.
Matilde!
Are we not friends anymore or what?
-That's what I've been wondering.
-Hmm.
Uh, you haven't
come to the house in a while.
The truth is, I barely have time
after the incident with José Arcadio.
-Mm. I can imagine.
-Hmm.
We all miss him a lot, that's for certain.
Hmm.
You know, the other day,
he was speaking to Father Nicanor.
If it hadn't been for him,
we wouldn't have
any idea what he's been saying.
Now he spends all day just chatting away,
like he used to with you.
He's a fine man, that Nicanor.
What, exactly,
are you trying to say, Úrsula?
Sometimes I feel like
your closeness to the Moscotes
has made you forget about
the town we founded with José Arcadio.
Unfortunately,
José Arcadio is tied up to a tree.
Now I have to look after my family.
My memory's unimpaired, Gerineldo.
That's how I know the two of you left
right in the middle of
my son Aureliano's wedding.
And I also know that the Moscotes
are the only ones
who have been to the house
since José Arcadio abandoned us all.
It was nice to see you.
Excuse me.
I've never understood…
the point of competition
between two adversaries
who share the same principles.
Hmm.
How could they possibly
tie you to a tree?
It's quite simple.
I'm crazy, Father.
Concerned about his own faith,
the priest never came to see him again.
Just one spoonful at least, my darling.
You mustn't starve
that child inside of you.
Hmm?
Hmm.
Mrs. Buendía.
With or without stained glass,
with or without bells,
Rebeca needs to be standing
at the altar at the end of the month.
Are we clear, Nicanor?
My love, good morning.
Write to your mom.
We're getting married within the month,
with or without her.
Amaranta had shaken with fear
waiting for that moment.
Ooh.
Oh, steady. Steady.
There you go.
What do you think? Boy or girl?
I don't know,
but we're expecting two, not one.
How would you know that though?
The same way I knew before Rebeca arrived,
that she would soon step through
our front door with frightened eyes.
Think I'm lying?
Ask Mother. She'll tell you about it.
Miguel!
Where were you?
-With Carlos. We're making this.
-What?
Come here.
Honey, what is that?
-I don't know. It feels funny.
-What happened?
It's good to see you.
Pilar!
Principal.
May I have a quick word?
-Oh, is Miguel in trouble?
-No, no. Of course not.
-Mind watching him for a moment?
-Yes.
Tell me.
After you.
No! No, no, no, no! José! Uh… No!
-No! Arcadio, no!
-Uh-huh.
No!
José, no! No!
No, no, no, no! No. No.
Don't act stupid. Huh?
Everybody in town knows you're a whore.
Not here. Not here.
-Mm.
-Not here! Not now!
My son's outside.
He could hear us. Arcadio.
Arcadio, no! Arcadio!
Mm.
I'll return.
I'll return tonight. You'll see.
Just leave the door open
and the lights off.
-Yeah? You sure?
-Yes?
What'd be the point
in lying to you, Arcadio?
Hmm?
Wait for me here tonight.
Miguel! Let's go.
He stayed up all night,
waiting for her,
listening to the agitated crickets
of the endless dawn,
growing more and more convinced
that he had been deceived.
Arcadio realized that this was
not the woman he was waiting for,
because she did not smell of smoke.
She was a virgin,
and her name was Santa Sofía de la Piedad.
Pilar Ternera had paid her fifty pesos,
half of her life savings,
to do what she was doing.
Arcadio had seen her many times,
but had never noticed her
because she had the rare virtue
of never existing completely,
except at the right time.
But from that day on,
he huddled like a cat
in the warmth of her armpit.
"…blessed is the fruit of
thy womb, Jesus. Holy Mary, Mother of God,
pray for us sinners."
"Lead not into temptation,
but deliver us from evil."
"Hail Mary, full of grace,
the Lord is with thee."
"Blessed art thou amongst women,
and blessed is the fruit
of thy womb, Jesus."
What?
Oh my…
Help! Reme! Reme, breathe!
Breathe!
Somebody help us!
Somebody get a doctor!
Mother!
Breathe, Remedios! Breathe! Look at me!
Look at me! I'm right here!
I'm right here, my love! My love?
My love, my love!
No, no. Look at me. Don't go to sleep.
Don't go to sleep. Don't go to sleep.
My love! Don't go to sleep, my darling!
Don't go to sleep!
Remedios died,
poisoned by an infection in her blood,
with a set of twins in her womb.
Today, more than ever,
given the terrible circumstances
that bring us together…
I give thanks to God
for His infinite wisdom and love…
for He has opened for us, just in time…
…the doors of His temple, of His house,
so we can leave
pain
and the weight of this tragedy here.
Amaranta had begged
with such fervor
for something horrible to happen,
so that she would not
have to poison Rebeca.
She felt guilty for the death of Remedios
and adopted Aureliano José
as the son that would keep her company
in her eternal solitude.
Úrsula ordered
a mourning period
of closed doors and windows.
And she forbade talking aloud
for an entire year.
When the mourning
had gone on long enough
for the cross-stitching sessions
to resume,
a gush of wind blew the doors open
at 2:00 in the afternoon.
It can't be.
No, it can't be. No! No!
It was José Arcadio.
He had returned as poor as he had left,
and even his father,
under the solitary of the chestnut tree,
had an impression that an earthquake
was tearing the house apart.
BASED ON THE NOVEL
BY GABRIEL GARCÍA MÁRQUEZ